Let us consider an example for
resolution, and let us do this
by looking at this example assuming
that we have the following query.
Yes, this query, consisting of two literals
involving variables and, in particular, also a
variable that occurs in more than one literal
because that's the case we have to deal with.
And let's also assume we have a
program and it has maybe many rules.
And one of them is this one, and this is
the one we are going to use in a moment.
But as you know, we could have, in principle,
taken any rule in a program if we can
actually apply a resolution step with
one of the literals in the query.
Okay, let me also further make decisions about
how to decompose the query, on slide 74,
there was this division into P or the
literals occurring before the literal
I'm interested in, then the literal
L, and then all the ones after that.
So, for this specific case, the way to look
at this would be that this is our interesting
literal L, yes, the one we want to focus on.
There's no P in advance so
there's an empty sequence here.
P would be empty, and then there is
this other sequence of queries, Q.
In this case, Q consists exactly
of one query, but of course,
there could be further ones and then the
remainder of the explanation would still apply.
Okay, so that's the choice of L
and Q in the spirit of slide 74.
And then I already mentioned that we assume
we have chosen this clause to resolve with.
And then, well, what does this mean?
Well, the head was called L0 in the slide,
and that's what we want to unify with L,
of course, in order to apply resolution.
And then the literals on
the right-hand side of the
clause that we’re going to
use are called L1 to Ln.
And of course, in this simple case n would
be one, and we have exactly only the L1.
Okay, so that's how the setup is here.
And then the slide says that we can apply a
resolution step if L and L0 are unifiable.
Okay, so that's the question we first have to
ask: are this L and this L0 actually unifiable?
So, that's something we always have to
do when we want to apply resolution.
Well, you could now go and apply an algorithm for
making this, or finding out if this is the case.
But of course, I already mentioned that you
don't always have to apply an algorithm.
We can simply look at our terms
and see what the solution...
Well, think about the choice that you have.
And then for example, here we see
that well, the X must be Juliet,
and Z must be Mary and then this
will be okay, this will fit.
And, of course, we have to
make these two decisions.
So, there's no choice, really.
There's nothing more general.
You can't leave a variable here in order to
unify this L and this, as you will really
have to make exactly these two choices.
So, the answer is yes, and the
most general unifier is as follows.
The most general unifier, it’s really
the substitution which replaces X by
Juliet and Z by Mary.
Okay, note that here already, the
variables are distinct in the rule
and in the query that we started
with; if that wouldn't be the case,
you might have first renamed the
variables in the program, right?
So, let's assume that this
would have been Y and Y here.
Then we could still unify L and
L0, but that will also touch the Y.
And that could be dangerous because
you also have a Y in the query.
We want to avoid this, so if we would have Y
in the program, you would maybe replace
Y1 or Y2 or something like this.
Or, well, actually by Z, since that
doesn't appear in the query, okay?
We didn't have to make this step of renaming
variables because already there are distinct
sets of variables in the query we are interested
in and the program rule that you want to apply.
Okay, so that's what we have.
We applied some algorithm for
identifying the most general unifier, or
got to it by having a deep look
at the two terms, L and L0.
So, now this is what we have.
And then what does the slide
say about applying resolution?
Well, one resolution step, right?
We do one step by another, and then we look
for the next query and see whether we can apply
another resolution step, or we do one resolution
step now and this gives us our new query,
the following.
Okay, we get, according to the slide, we get the
unifier U applied to all the literals from P.
Now the P are the things that would have occurred
up here in the query before the
literal L that we chose to resolve.
Since there are the literals in front there,
of course, also applying U to
them doesn't give anything new.
Okay, then comes not L, but actually L1, yes.
So, after you have applied U to the literals
which would have occurred before in the query,
we then apply U to all the literals on the
right-hand side of the rule that we used.
Yes, so here we have to write something
like U(L1) and U(Q) according to the slide.
And U(P) is not present
because it doesn't even exist.
P does not exist.
Okay, so what is U(L1)?
Well, here we have L1.
U is this unifier, the substitution.
So, what does it do?
It replaces that by Mary and that is
the only variable that occurs in L1.
So, what we get here is the
new literal with Mary for that.
And of course, Paul is unchanged because
it isn't a variable and it doesn't
contain a variable, okay?
So, that is the unifier applied to L1 to
the right-hand side of the rule we applied
after we unified L and L0, okay?
And then the slide says that in
addition, we can't forget about the Q.
We also have to keep the Q, the context
of this literal that we resolved.
But of course, we don't keep Q itself; we
keep the application of the unifier to this Q.
So, what does this mean?
The Q contained is just this one literal
containing Y and X; Y isn't even mentioned here.
So, it's left unchanged, but X is
replaced by Juliet in the unifier.
So, what we get is the second literal here
where the first argument is still the variable Y
but the second argument is now
the variable X replaced by Juliet.
And there is no further stuff because
Q consists exactly of this one literal.
If there were more literals in
Q, then these would also be
replicated here with the unifier applied.
Okay, and now this is our new
query, and maybe we can now look for
some rules which tell us when this is the case,
or we could do the same for the second literal.
So, we have more choices here, depending
on what rules we have also in the program.
But this is one step that we are seeing here.
And what does it tell us?
Well, it tells us if you wanted to prove
this, then it's now good enough to prove this.
So, intuitively, you've wanted to look for the
sister of Mary, which is the daughter of Y.
And knowing that Juliet is the sister of anybody
who is the mother of Paul, we now know, well,
if Mary is the mother of Paul, then it's
enough to look for the father of Juliet.
Because if Mary is the mother of Paul, then
Juliet is the sister of Mary, and we know that
well, we’re looking for someone who is a
sister of Mary, but also fathered by Y.
And now that would be established, if you
find these persons down here in this query.
It's not the only choice because there could
have been further rules in the program.
For example, establishing that someone
is the sister of someone else.
And then that would be other proof approaches.
And maybe one of them leads to a
solution, the other doesn't but
then we need to perform further
resolution steps to find out.
Here, we did exactly one step and
that's the base ingredient here,
which will be used then in the search process
when we look at derivation trees next week.
Okay, you will also find at least one
further example of such a resolution step
in the collection.pdf in the Moodle course.